Rollin Crampton Papers
Rollin Crampton Papers
1945-1964
Crampton, Rollin McNeil, 1886-1970.
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American painter, sculptor (1886-1970). Copies of letters received, 1952-1964; exhibition notices and photographs of work; manuscript 'Laws of Proportion', 1964; also published materials.
148911
Biographical History
Rollin Crampton (1886-1970) was an American painter and illustrator known for his geometric abstractions.
Born in New Haven, Connecticut, Crampton studied at Yale University School of Fine Arts and won a scholarship from the Art Student's League. In 1936 he was appointed mural supervisor for the New York City Art Project. He was the recipient of two Purchase Prizes (SUNY New Paltz and Lousiana State University); his work was exhibited at museums and galleries across the country (including the Museum of Modern Art) and is in the permanent collections of the Whitney Museum of American Art and the Albright Gallery.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Rollin Crampton Papers consist of biographical material, correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, and published material.
Biographical material contains a biographical sketch by Crampton for the Program Director of the Longview Foundation.
Correspondence is incoming only; the majority are photostats, not originals. Included in the photostats are letters from art critic Clement Greenberg and artist Jackson Pollock.
Subject files contains exhibit notices, a genealogy of Mrs. Crampton, and photographs of Crampton, his work, and others.
Manuscripts contains a one-page manuscript entitled "Laws of proportion."
Published material consists of a newspaper and magazine clippings about Crampton and his work.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has the papers of more than one hundred painters, illustrators, and other artists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Painters; Crampton, Rollin McNeil, 1886-1970 -- Archives.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Artists.; Painters.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Rollin Crampton, 1964-1968.
Inventory
- Biographcal material
  - Letter (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - E-R, 1952; 1954,; 1960-1961,; 1964,; undated (Box 1)
  - Greenberg, Clement, 1960; photostat (Box 1)
  - Pollock, Jackson, undated; letter about Crampton; photostat (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, 1952-1954; undated; photostat (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Exhibit notices, 1945; 1946,; 1948,; 1951,; 1954,; 1956,; 1959-1960,; undated (Box 1)
  - Genealogy of wife, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - of Crampton, undated (Box 1)
    - of others, undated (Box 1)
    - of Crampton's work, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - "Laws of proportion", 1964 (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Magazine articles
    - about Crampton and others, Art Digest, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Photocopies, 1954; 1959-1960,; undated (Box 1)
  - Newspaper, Hue and Cry, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - about Crampton and others, 1951; 1960,; undated (Box 1)
    - Photocopies, 1958-1960; undated (Box 1)